Early 1944, Nazi Germany. Allied bombing has reduced production of aircraft.
combat of German factories by up to two-thirds. To reduce the effectiveness of
Allied bombing, the German Armaments Ministry led by Albert Speer and the SS agree
accelerate the construction of huge underground factories to move production there.
New concrete bunkers will be built for prisoners in this way.
of the concentration camps, because the existing underground areas, such as caves and mines,
They are not suitable for industrial production. In 1944 and 1945, they were established throughout the Reich.
German hundreds of satellite camps attached to the main concentration camps,
where inmates are forced to dig into mountainsides or caves
to create immense tunnel systems and factories to develop and build new weapons,
such as remote weapons, controlled anti-aircraft rockets or strategic bombers
that would be capable of attacking the United States from Germany. One of these fields is Ebensee,
which will be operational for a year and a half and will claim the lives of at least 8,200 people,
one third of the prisoners held there. They will be subjected to brutal mistreatment,
torture and starvation. However, after the liberation of the camp, the released prisoners were
They will take extremely violent revenge for the atrocities inflicted upon them.
Between 1940 and 1945, the SS authorities established about 50 subcamps in the
Mauthausen concentration camp system. These subcamps were generally located in
the vicinity of factories, stone quarries and mines, where officers of
SS manpower allocation deployed prisoners transferred from the camp
Mauthausen's main camp. Among the most important of these subcamps was Ebensee, with the
codenamed "Zement", which was located in the vicinity of the town of Ebensee in
Upper Austria. Together with the Mauthausen subcamp of Gusen, Ebensee, founded on 18 November 1968,
1943, belonged to one of the harshest concentration camps ever built.
Most of the Ebensee prisoners had been transferred from the concentration camp
from Mauthausen in Austria and the first large transport of 1,000 prisoners from Mauthausen
arrived at Ebensee on November 19, 1943, one day after the camp was established. He barely
There was accommodation to protect the first group of prisoners from the cold Austrian winter and the
The death toll increased considerably. The bodies piled up, and every 3 or 4 days
They were taken to the Mauthausen crematorium to be burned, since Ebensee did not yet have its own crematorium.
crematorium. The dead were also piled up inside the few huts that existed and the smell
of the dead, combined with nausea, abscesses, urine and feces, was unbearable. In the middle of
In 1944, Ebensee got its own crematorium with a huge single chimney rising into the
air. Other buildings were also built. In one of them, block 23,
great piles of dead and people still alive. When the field was full,
Up to 600 prisoners lay on the bare ground at the same time. One day in April 1945,
In block 23 alone, a record number of eighty bodies were removed.
The main objective of Ebensee was to provide slave labor for the construction of
huge tunnels in the mountains, which would house weapons factories safely
of the bombings, as well as the development of the Waterfall and American Bomber projects. While
that Waterfall was a project to develop guided supersonic surface-to-air missiles,
The “American Bomber” project was an initiative of the German Ministry of Aviation to obtain
a long-range strategic bomber for the Luftwaffe (the German Air Force)
that would be capable of attacking the United States - specifically New York City
York - from Germany, a round trip distance of approximately 11,600 km or 7,200
miles. Both projects were not completed. Although production was planned for
Tank transmissions will be carried out within the “A” tunnel system,
The project was replaced by the construction of an underground refinery,
Since fuel production became a priority, crude oil distillation
in the "A" tunnel system, which was almost completed when the war ended,
began in February 1945. In the "B" tunnel system, which at the end of the war was
60 percent complete, ball bearing manufacturing was underway.
By May 1944 there were 5,000 prisoners in the Ebensee subcamp, and by the end of the year,
There were more than 9,000. The largest number of prisoners present at one time was 18,509, a figure
which was reached on April 23, 1945. At that time, overcrowding in Ebensee was so great
that more prisoners were dying every day than the crematorium could hold. In April 1945,
4,547 out of a total population of 16,000 people lost their lives in Ebensee.
In total, some 27,000 prisoners were held captive at Ebensee.
Living conditions here were worse than in most other subcamps.
The field was surrounded by a barbed wire fence, small machine gun towers and huts
for the SS. New prisoners were sometimes kept in quarantine for two weeks
to break them both physically and mentally. The prisoners wore wooden clogs and when these
shoes fell apart and the inmates had to walk barefoot because there weren't enough for everyone.
This was especially painful during the long winter from November 1943 to June 1944,
when the last traces of snow were barely disappearing and the prisoners sometimes had
to remain barefoot. Otherwise, the prisoners did not have
with enough clothing for these conditions. The barracks had no heating, there was no
bathrooms, lice infested the camp and the sawdust from the mattresses made the prisoners suffer.
The works in the aforementioned tunnels were often ordered by the supervisors
as a repressive measure. Prisoners worked 11-hour shifts unless they were
working in the tunnels, when they were on one of the three 8-hour shifts. For their part,
The rations were insufficient: the average daily ration was around 700 kcal. They consisted of half
liter of coffee for breakfast, three-quarters of a liter of hot water with potato peels
for lunch and 150 grams of bread with water for dinner. The prisoners always spent
hunger and about a third of the inmates were constantly on the verge of starvation.
Those who worked within the field and were assigned, for example, to administrative tasks,
They did not have to work as hard as those assigned to work outside
from the countryside. Many companies were hired to supervise the construction work.
of the tunnel and these companies provided civilian workers, each of whom
supervised several prisoners at work. The SS, wanting to please the companies,
tried to provide them with the number of prisoners they requested, even if
Those prisoners were dying. SS soldiers and prisoner officials designated
called Kapos also supervised the prisoners with varying degrees of
brutality. When new inmates arrived at the camp, the veteran prisoners soon
They were informed that there was only one way out: through the crematorium chimney.
Ebensee consisted of several groups of prisoners, such as prisoners of war,
political prisoners, criminals, as well as Roma and Sinti. Here there were
inmates of 20 different nationalities, including Poles,
Russians, Hungarians, Italians, and Spaniards. The mortality rate of prisoners
Italians in Ebensee was 53%. The reason was that after the fall of Mussolini in 1943,
The Italians were branded traitors by both their fellow communist prisoners
and by both fascists and National Socialists. Of the 955 Italian prisoners, 512 died.
The lowest mortality rate, 0.9 percent, was for Spanish prisoners.
The first Jews arrived in Ebensee at the beginning of June 1944 and constituted
approximately one-third of the inmates. They were subjected to extremely cruel treatment and,
As a result, their mortality rate was nearly 40 percent, much higher than the
from the rest of the rural population. When, for example, on March 3,
In 1945, more than 2,000 Jewish prisoners arrived from the Gross-Rosen subcamp in Wolfsberg,
The Ebensee commander, Anton Ganz, forced them to stay outside for almost two
days during the snow. Hundreds of them died from exhaustion caused by the
transportation to the field and exposure to such weather conditions.
The first commandant of Ebensee was Georg Bachmayer, who made it one of the most important camps
concentration camps ever built. One of the most popular methods of torture was
tying a prisoner's arms behind him, with his hands side by side and thumb to thumb
by thumb, and then suspend them from a tree about forty centimeters from the ground. Then,
Bachmayer would unleash his favorite dog, a German Shepherd named "Lord," to attack
to the prisoners, who would be left to die a slow and agonizing death.
Bachmayer was replaced in his post by SS Hauptsturmführer Alfons Bentele and at the beginning
In 1944, Obersturmfûhrer Otto Riemer was appointed the new commander at Ebensee.
During his tenure, conditions deteriorated further. He personally beat,
He shot and tortured prisoners daily. He openly offered extra cigarettes and permission
to those sentinels who could represent the greatest number of deaths. If a sentinel at the
At the end of the day he didn't have enough numbers to his name, he would take off a prisoner's cap.
and threw it into a restricted area. When the inmate went to retrieve it, he would be shot.
Riemer, like Bachmayer, was a great lover of wine and women,
and used to go on drunken bender with some of the younger members of the SS. On one occasion,
On May 18, 1944, he returned to camp after a lifelong drinking session.
at night with 12 members of his SS command. They entered the camp firing wildly with their
guns and roaring with joy as the panicked prisoners moved away
of his way. Fifteen prisoners died as a result of this exhibition. After this,
Riemer was demoted and transferred to the camp post office.
Gusen concentration camp. The last commander of Ebensee was SS Hauptsturmführer Anton Ganz.
For their part, the kapos were especially cruel. The leader of block 19 expected
that his prisoners returned from the day's work and then forced them to perform exhausting
physical exercises until late at night. The next morning, after a sleepless night,
The men were forced to work another full day. Almost all members of their block
They died of exhaustion within ten days. With this system of elimination, he managed to kill the
prisoners in the most economical way and was rewarded. When Wels was built, another
subcamp of the Mauthausen concentration camp, became the camp leader.
As the war was coming to an end, the mass evacuation of other camps exerted
tremendous pressure on the Mauthausen complex, which was the last camp that
was in the Nazi zone of power. The 25 Ebensee barracks were designed to
house 100 prisoners each, but at that time some of them housed
at 750. There were also prisoners who were kept in the tunnel systems and at
open air. The crematorium could not keep up with the number of deaths and naked bodies.
lay piled up outside the blocks and the crematorium itself. In the final weeks of the war,
The mortality rate exceeded 350 per day. The camp commandant, Anton Ganz,
ordered the excavation of two secret mass graves to dispose of 2,167 bodies. The bodies
They were thrown into the quicklime, and in the pile, their feet were seen still trembling.
In early May 1945, gunshots could be heard in the distance from inside the camp,
and there was a feeling among the prisoners that the American and British forces
were close. On May 5, camp commandant Anton Ganz attempted to have the prisoners
remaining to enter one of the mountain tunnels. However, they refused,
They remained in their barracks and the camp staff left, leaving only elderly Germans
armed with rifles to guard the camp. When the prisoners realized that
The SS had abandoned the camp, killed 52 camp officials who had collaborated with
the SS to create the hierarchy of that place. Shortly after the liberation, the troops
Americans discovered that the tunnel that the Ebensee commander had tried to reach
to attract the remaining prisoners, supposedly to protect them, was packed with explosives.
By refusing to enter the tunnel, the prisoners were saved from being blown up by the Germans.
Of the 27,000 prisoners held at Ebensee, more than 8,200 died.
before liberation, making the mortality rate in the Ebensee subcamp 31
percent. After the liberation, US troops requisitioned local food and
They prepared soup for the prisoners. However, some died from a ruptured stomach,
due to the fact that they had not consumed solid food for so long.
In total, more than 730 prisoners died in the weeks following their release as a result
from their imprisonment and 1,000 remained in hospitals for an extended period.
Ben Ferencz, chief prosecutor for the United States Army in the Einsatzgruppen trial,
who participated in the liberation of Ebensee in May 1945 and investigated the events there,
He noted the following: "I directed a group of Germans who were passing by to help
to bury the bodies of the prisoners scattered across the camp grounds. There,
Some prisoners caught one of the SS guards as he tried to escape.
Given the violence of the attack, it could have been the camp commander. First they beat him.
mercilessly. Then the crowd tied him to one of the metal trays used to slide
bodies to the crematorium. There they were slowly roasted alive, being put in and taken out of the oven
several times. I saw it happen and did nothing. It wasn't my duty to stop it, even if I could have,
And frankly, I wasn't about to try. There seemed to be no limit to human brutality.
in wartime. I headed back to Munich to write my reports. These
would serve as the basis for later war crimes trials. I was grateful that the
war was coming to an end. I learned that there never has been, nor will there ever be, a war without
atrocities. The only way to prevent such cruel crimes was to prevent war itself."
Many tears were shed for all the victims of the Ebensee concentration camp.
Thank you for watching World History Channel
I forgot to like, subscribe, and click the notification bell.
Don't miss our next videos thanks See you next time on the channel